Guide to the Montana Legislative Assembly (9th: 1905) records 1904-1905
Montana Historical Society Research Center
Montana Legislative Assembly (9th: 1905) records
1904-1905
Montana Historical Society Archives
LR 9
Montana. Legislative Assembly.
.6 linear feet of shelf space
Records of the Montana 9th Legislative Assembly consist of reports of Joint and Senate special committees; correspondence; subject files on contested elections; certificates of election; and petitions, including some for women's suffrage. [OVERSIZE MATERIAL: Box #1, map case]
The Montana State Legislature is made up of two chambers, the Senate and the House of Representatives. The Constitution of Montana limits the size of the Senate to no fewer than 40 and no more than 50 members and the size of the House of Representatives to no fewer than 80 and no more than 100 members. Each house is responsible for choosing its officers, creating committees and establishing its own rules. The Montana Legislature meets for 90 days every odd numbered year, beginning the first Monday in January, or the following Wednesday if the first Monday is New Years Day. The first State Legislature convened on November 23, 1889, fifteen days after Montana became a state. Each following Legislature has been numbered sequentially.
The 9th Montana Legislature met from January 2nd to March 2nd, 1905. The leaders of the Senate were Edwin Norris (D-President), and Benjamin White (R-President Pro Tempore). The leaders of the House were Wyllis Hedges (R-Speaker), and Marcus Hewett (R-Speaker Pro Tempore).
Sources:The Constitution of the State of Montana as adopted by the Constitutional Convention March 22, 1972, and as ratified by the people, June 6, 1972, referendum no. 68, "A GUIDE TO THE MONTANA LEGISLATURE," The Montana Legislature,; “Montana Legislative Leadership 1889 – Present”.
Records (1904-1905) of the Montana 9th Legislative Assembly consist of reports of Special Joint Committee to Investigate the Condition and Needs of the Agriculture College and State Reform School (includes only the report on the State Reform School), the Special Joint Committee to Investigate the Management of the State Penitentiary, the House Special Committee to Investigate the State Agricultural College, the Senate Special Committee to Investigate the Condition of the State Insane Asylum, Special Committee to Investigate the State School of Mines, and Special Committee to Investigate the University of Montana; correspondence; subject files on contested elections; certificates of election; and petitions, including some for women's suffrage. [OVERSIZE MATERIAL: Box #1, map case]
The collection is organized into six series, House and Senate Joint Committees (arranged alphabetically), House of Representatives Special Committees and Resolutions (arranged by committees and then resolutions), Senate Speical Committees (arranged alphabetically), General Correpsondence (arranged alphabetically), Subject Files (arranged alphabetically), Miscellany (arranged alphabetically).
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request
OVERSIZE MATERIAL: oversize box #1, map case
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Bills, Legislative--Montana.; Legislative bodies--Montana--Committees.; Women Suffrage--Montana.
Montana--Politics and government.
Montana.; Government and Politics.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- House and Senate Joint Committees
  - Special Joint Committee to Investigate the Condition and Needs of the Agriculture College and State Reform School (includes only the report on the State Reform School), 1905 March (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - Special Joint Committee to Investigate the Management of the State Penitentiary (re allegations made by Thomas F. O'Brien in Infamy and Immortal, 1904), 1905 February (Box-folder 1 / 2)
- House of Representatives Special Committees and Resolutions
  - Special Committee to Investigate the State Agriculture College, 1905 February 20 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
  - House Concurrent Resolution 10 (opposing a measure to create one State from the Territories of Arizona and New Mexico, 1905 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
- Senate Special Committees
  - Special Committee to Investigate the Condition of the State Insane Asylum, 1905 February 28 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
  - Special Committee to Investigate the State School of Mines, 1905 February 28 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - Special Committee to Investigate the University of Montana, 1905 February 23 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
- General Correspondence
  - To the House Appropriations Committee from the University of Montana, 1905 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
  - To the Senate from the Executive Office, 1905 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
- Subject Files
  - Contested Elections: John McCullough vs. E.E. Huntington (re Carbon County House Seat), 1904 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
  - Contested Elections: James McGowan vs. James S. Schoonover (re Granite County House Seat), 1904 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
  - Contested Elections: T. Wesley Richardson vs. M.A. Wellman (re Lewis and Clark County House Seat) [OVERSIZE MATERIAL: oversize box #1, map case], 1904 (Box-folder 1 / 12)
  - Contested Elections: Louis Rotwitt vs. B.F. Bembrick (re Broadwater County House Seat; Includes a transcript of testimony), 1904 (Box-folder 1 / 13)
- Miscellany
  - Certificates of elections [OVERSIZE MATERIAL: oversize box #1], 1904 (Box-folder 1 / 14)
  - Petitions (supporting HB 55, prohibiting the sale of liquors to minors), 1905 (Box-folder 1 / 15)
  - Petitions (supporting the initiative and the referendum of constitutional amendments to voters), 1905 (Box-folder 1 / 16)
  - Petitions (re support of legislation compelling enforcement of the gambling law; opposing changes in the county printing law; opposing reduction in liquor tax paid by grocers; supporting repeal of the state and county license of merchants, professional men, boarding houses, restaurants, etc.; supporting actions of the Montana Anglers Club of Butte; supporting direct legislation; and censuring Jefferson County High School's opposition of women's suffrage), 1905 (Box-folder 1 / 17)
  - Petitions for women's suffrage: Butte, 1905 (Box-folder 1 / 18-19)
  - Petitions for women's suffrage: Helena, Bald Butte, 1905 (Box-folder 1 / 20-21)
  - Petitions for women's suffrage: Alhambra, Gebo, Red Lodge, Jefferson County, Whitehall, 1905 (Box-folder 1 / 22)
  - Petitions for women's suffrage: Custer County, Miles City, Anaconda, Great Falls, DeBorgia, Hamilton, 1905 (Box-folder 1 / 23)
  - Petitions for women's suffrage: Big Timber, Winston, Ada, Stockett, Twin Bridges, New Year Club, White Sulphur Springs, Deer Lodge, Race Track, Pioneer, Garrison, Elliston, 1905 (Box-folder 1 / 24)
  - Petitions for women's suffrage: Kalispell, Libby, Boulder, Five Mile, 1905 (Box-folder 1 / 25)